Ou, Changkun

Curriculum Vitae

Frauenlobstr. 7a Science and art, life in between 80337 Munich, Germany

**** +49 157 7214 1480 / +86 186 1322 5636

changkun.de 😯 @changkun 😯

Born on October 25th 1993 in Zhijiang/Hunan/China

People's Republic of China citizenship

Single

Last update: April 15, 2020

Note: colored texts contains clickable URL.

Introduction

Changkun Ou is a research assistant at the University of Munich. His research topics are interdisciplinary in computational geometry, imitation learning, and human-computer interaction. In particular, he would like to leverage three-dimensional polygonal mesh representation learning and visual preference elicitation to develop efficient algorithms or industrial tools for 3D modeling and rendering.

Education

University of Munich (LMU) Ph.D. Candidate in Media Informatics.

Munich, Germany Feb. 2019 - Present

o Publications: Link

University of Munich

Munich, Germany

Master of Science in Computer Science; GPA: 2.05 in scale of 1.00 (best) to 4.0

Apr. 2018 - Present

University of Munich

Munich, Germany

Master of Science in Human-Computer Interaction (HCI); GPA: 1.63 in scale of 1.00 (best)

Oct. 2016 - Jan. 2019

to 5.0, "qut".

• Thesis: Understanding and Predicting Web Browsing Behavior.

University of Electronic Science and Technology of China (UESTC)

Chengdu, China Aug. 2016 - Sep. 2016

Master of Engineering in Software Engineering

Southwest University for Nationalities (SWUN)

Chengdu, China

Bachelor of Engineering in Computer Science; Grade: 3.74 in scale of 4.00 (best) to 1.0, "Top 1 Student".

Sep. 2012 - Jul. 2016

• Thesis: Designing Alternative Contact-free Control Modalities for Smart Watches.

First Middle School of Zhijiang

Huaihua, China

Senior Middle School; With university entrance examination (Gaokao)

Mar. 2010 - Jul. 2012

Changsha Foreign Language School

Changsha, China

Second Middle School of Zhijiang

Aug. 2009 - Feb. 2010

Junior Middle School

Senior Middle School

Sep.2006 - Jul.2009

Chengnan Primary School of Zhijiang

Huaihua, China

Primary School

Huaihua, China Sep. 2000 - Jul. 2006

Work Experiences

Munich, Germany Aprl. 2018 - Present

Research Assistant University of Munich

o DevOps: Compatability development and migration of a 15 years old CMS system (2005).

• Teaching Assistant: Computer Graphics

o Teaching Assistant: Online Multimedia

o Teaching Assistant: Seminar Advances in Computer Graphics

• Tutor: Deep Learning and Artificial Intelligence, notes on GitHub

o Tutor: Machine Learning, notes on GitHub.

Backend Engineer (Remote)

LabEx Technology Ltd

Chengdu, China Apr. 2018 – Jan. 2019

• Team leader and leading backend development of the oversea product: I lead and responsible for the product development in backend and frontend. I evolve the existing architecture and split a monolithic backend web application into multiple microservices. The product scales machine cluster from 20 to 200 for active daily users, and its user group increases from 5k to 30k during my incumbency.

- Remote desktop Control Proxy: I responsible and developed a middleware that provides generic remote desktop proxy in Go. The proxy translates VNC/RDP/SSH protocol data, and establish WebSocket connection to a web browser for providing remote desktop GUI.
- Multi-cloud automation: I developed a fully automated multi-cloud resource management microservice in Go. The service defines a general abstraction cross all cloud provider, it automatically manages all user requested resources allocation and releases outdated resources. For instance, a user of the service can allocate new cloud instances for temporal using without noticing the instance was allocated in either AWS, AlibabaCloud, or others. The service supports more than 15 cloud products and integrated 3 cloud providers, being able to support almost unlimited concurrent users and has been used by 10k+ users.
- Cluster management service: I developed a microservice in Go that similar to Kubernetes and Docker Swarm. The service manages multiple server clusters, and auto-scaling its cluster size upon request cross multiple cloud providers. Each cluster contains multiple physical machines, and each machine runs many docker containers. The key feature of the service eliminates the difference between the physical machine and the docker container. The runtime of the service includes a system monitor with request prediction algorithm that I invented for efficient auto-scaling with consideration of overcommit ratio and a task scheduler for managing all distributed asynchronous task execution with two-level caching optimization.
- **Used tech. stack**: Vue, jQuery, Webpack, Electron; Backend: Go, Cgo, Gin, Beego, gRPC, MySQL, MongoDB, Redis, Hypervisor, Nginx, Docker, Kubernetes, AWS, AlibabaCloud, etc.

Fullstack Engineer (Freelance)

Rocketlingo UG

Munich, Germany

Nov. 2017 - Mar. 2018

- Language Teaching Voice Bot: I am part of the team in developing a voice bot that provides English learning teaching service. The bot can communicate with its user and improve their English skill by the real-time response. My responsibility is to implement the backend support designed conversations using Amazon Alexa.
- Speech Recognition Solution & Web Development: I responsible for the development of speech recognition solution over web technologies, such as using WebSocket for audio streaming, using Google Cloud STT and TTS services for speech recognition and synthesis, etc. The challenging part of using existing speech recognition service for a language learning application is a new language learner sometimes does not produces positive audio samples, and even multilingual. Therefore, I developed many text-based falt tolerances technique for improving the understanding of user speech based on machine learning algorithms.
- Used Tech. Stack: Frontend: Angular, Backend: NodeJS, ExpressJS, WebSocket, Python, Flask, MongoDB,
 Elasticsearch, AWS Serverless, Tensorflow, Numpy, Matplotlib

Shiyanlou

Chengdu, China

Jun. 2016 - Sep. 2016

Software Engineer (Intern)

- Recommendation System: Online course recommendation system; Python; MongoDB; Collaborate Filtering
- o Distributed Log System: Elasticsearch; Logstash; Kibana; Redis
- Cross Platform Desktop Client: Electron based development for macOS/Windows/Linux
- Teaching Meterial Writing: Modern C++ based teaching meterial writing

Academic Tutor

Chengdu, China

Jul. 2015

SWUN Lecture "Human-Computer Interaction"

Skills

- I have good skills in web development and machine learning. and I can use the following languages: go; python; javascript; c/c++ (for optimization); markdown; IATEX; native Chinese; fluent professional English; elementary German
- Certificates: Coursera, Andrew Ng: Deep Learning Specializations, certificates: 1, 2, 3, 4, 5

Open Source Contribution

- Tensorflow (137k+ stars): Contributor
- Go (65.9k+ stars): Contributor
- etcd (28.2k+ stars): Contributor
- Modern C++ Tutorial (5.1k+ stars): I am the author of the book. The book provides the state-of-the-art content towards modern C++, which includes C++11/14/17/20.
- Go under the hood (1.2k stars): I am the author of the book. The book discusses Go source code, includes its runtime scheduler, garbage collection, compiler and etc.
- Official Tensorflow document translation (3.5k+ stars): I am the main contributor and project maintainer.
- Juejin Translation Public Community (22.6k+ stars): Major contributor, translated 50+ articles. Main reviewer of AI related articles.
- The Swift Programming Language Chinses Translation (18.7k+ stars): Major contributor (in Swift 1.x). The translation was officially acknowledged by Apple Inc.
- occamy: The project implements a modern remote desktop proxy written in Go. It provides web browser GUI for connecting vnc/rdp/ssh servers.
- gomat: The package provides cache-aware lock-free tiling optimization matrix utilities in Go.
- sched: The package for a high performance reliable task scheduling in Go.
- Check my GitHub homepage for more projects: github.com/changkun

Selected Talks

- Changkun Ou. *Understanding Communicating Sequential Processes*. Go Night Reading Meetup, 2019. English.
- Changkun Ou. Simplicity is complicated: On the balance of performance and knobs. Internal Doctoral Colloquium Autumn, 2019. English.
- Changkun Ou. Real-world Go Concurrency Bugs. Go Night Reading Meetup, 2019. Chinese.
- Changkun Ou. Internals of Channel and Select in Go. Go Night Reading Meetup, 2019. Chinese.
- Changkun Ou. *Identifying Malicious Players in GWAP-based Disaster Monitoring Crowdsourcing System*. ICAIBD 2019. English.
- Changkun Ou. *Understanding Generalization in Deep Learning*. Advanced Seminar Deep Learning, IFI LMU, 2018. English, Video.

Open Source Contribution

- Tensorflow (137k+ stars): Contributor
- Go (65.9k+ stars): Contributor
- etcd (28.2k+ stars): Contributor
- Modern C++ Tutorial (5.1k+ stars): I am the author of the book. The book provides the state-of-the-art content towards modern C++, which includes C++11/14/17/20.
- Go under the hood (1.2k stars): I am the author of the book. The book discusses Go source code, includes its runtime scheduler, garbage collection, compiler and etc.
- Official Tensorflow document translation (3.5k+ stars): I am the main contributor and project maintainer.
- Juejin Translation Public Community (22.6k+ stars): Major contributor, translated 50+ articles. Main reviewer of AI related articles.
- The Swift Programming Language Chinses Translation (18.7k+ stars): Major contributor (in Swift 1.x). The translation was officially acknowledged by Apple Inc.
- occamy: The project implements a modern remote desktop proxy written in Go. It provides web browser GUI for connecting vnc/rdp/ssh servers.
- gomat: The package provides cache-aware lock-free tiling optimization matrix utilities in Go.
- sched: The package for a high performance reliable task scheduling in Go.
- Check my GitHub homepage for more projects; github.com/changkun Page 3 of 4

Public Activities

Presenter

 at The ACM CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems

 Student Volunteer

 at Conference Smart Graphics 2015
 Guigu Lab Team Leader

 at SWUN
 Chengdu, China Sep. 2014 – Jun. 2015
 Mathematical Modeling Association Academic Vice Director

 Chengdu, China Oct. 2012 – Jun. 2014

 Chengdu, China Oct. 2012 – Jun. 2014

 2012 – Jun. 2014

 2012 – Jun. 2014

 2012 – Jun. 2014

	Chengdu, China Oct. 2012 – Jun. 2014
Honors & Awards	
• Siemens AILab Hackathon 2nd Winner	Munich, Germany Nov. 2017
$ \begin{array}{c} \textbf{China National Scholarship} \\ at \ \textit{UESTC} \end{array} $	Chengdu, China Sep. 2016
Excellent Bachelor Graduation Thesis Award $at \ SWUN$	Chengdu, China Jun. 2016
Best University Graduates Student Award at Sichuan Province	Chengdu, China Jan. 2016
Outstanding Student Scholarship $at \ SWUN$	Chengdu, China Nov. 2015
Student Innovative Annual Excellent Project $at SWUN$	Chengdu, China Jun. 2015
Sichuan Province Computer Production Competition 2nd Award	Chengdu, China May 2015
China National Scholarship $at \ SWUN$	Chengdu, China Sep. 2014
• American Mathematical Contest in Modeling(MCM) 2014 • Meritorious Winner	Chengdu, China <i>Apr. 2014</i>

Personal Interests

- Open source contributions: Writting open source book; Contributing and maintaining open source softwares
- Video blogging: Making videos on YouTube channel
- Blogging and knowledge sharing: on https://changkun.de
- Video gaming: Sony Playstation and Nintendo Switch player

References

- Prof. Andreas Butz: currently supervise for Master studies at LMU Munich Medieninformatik, Munich, Germany
- Prof. Heinrich Hußmann: exchange student course "Human-Computer Interaction I" at Southwest University for Nationalities, Chengdu, China
- Dr. Daniel Buschek: currently supervise for Master thesis at LMU Munich Medieninformatik, Munich, Germany
- Malin Eiband: currently supervise for Master thesis at LMU Munich Medieninformatik, Munich, Germany
- Florian Lachner: supervised for individual practical course at LMU Munich Medieninformatik, Munich, Germany
- Prof. Yaxi Chen: supervised for bachelor thesis at Southwest University for Nationalities, Chengdu, China
- Prof. Wei Zhou: supervised for bachelor thesis at Southwest University for Nationalities, Chengdu, China